<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jaydevsr.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://jaydevsr.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-08-07T08:27:12+00:00</updated><id>https://jaydevsr.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Bits of typing.</title><subtitle>I am Jaydev and this is my blog. Nothing more than that. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Burning Ice: A short poem</title><link href="https://jaydevsr.github.io/blog/writings/poem-burning-ice/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Burning Ice: A short poem" /><published>2024-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jaydevsr.github.io/blog/writings/poem-burning-ice</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jaydevsr.github.io/blog/writings/poem-burning-ice/"><![CDATA[<p>What follows is a poem of sorts that I wrote on the October 17th last year. Although I don’t claim any familiarity in the
literary genre of English poetry, this was a humble attempt. The topic is death in its natural form which is romanticised
as an ultimate end to all of the sufferings of the human condition. This is an unusual thing for me to write about as I am the kind
of person who fears untimely death because of all the greedy goals I harbor in my mind. Still, on that day it seems I did
write this for reasons which I don’t remember at all. I recently found this in my Google Keep and thought that I won’t be affected
anymore by any sort of judgement from whoever reads this. So, here goes nothing:</p>

<hr />

<p><strong>Burning Ice</strong> (17/10/2023)</p>

<p><i>
Have you ever been so cold?<br />
You are walking down a sunny lane,<br />
and a cold gust of wind penetrates you.<br />
For you bones were always a myth,<br />
You would have never known their existence.<br />
You now know them very well.<br />
You can feel something frozen to ice.<br />
<br />
You are so desperate now,<br />
You look for an escape.<br />
You run, jump and stomp the ground,<br />
But nothing calms you down.<br />
You light your clothes on fire,<br />
But you realize it just burns your skin.<br />
You are more miserable than before.<br />
You are to exist forever with burning skin,<br />
You are to exist forever with frozen bones.<br />
<br />
Then you see them burn the dead.<br />
Now you know how much more to wait<br />
till you are free from this tug of war,<br />
till you are free from the haunting burns,<br />
and till you are free from the frozen pain.<br />
You will go down the same sunny lane,<br />
In the land where there will be no you.<br />
</i></p>

<hr />

<p>P.S.: Something to note about this is that by choice I divided the stanzas into 7-9-7 lines and every line contains the word “You”. 
This is probably just me trying to be act like I know how poetry works LOL. It’s always so fun to make fun of your past self,
isn’t it?</p>]]></content><author><name>Jaydev</name></author><category term="Writings" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What follows is a poem of sorts that I wrote on the October 17th last year. Although I don’t claim any familiarity in the literary genre of English poetry, this was a humble attempt. The topic is death in its natural form which is romanticised as an ultimate end to all of the sufferings of the human condition. This is an unusual thing for me to write about as I am the kind of person who fears untimely death because of all the greedy goals I harbor in my mind. Still, on that day it seems I did write this for reasons which I don’t remember at all. I recently found this in my Google Keep and thought that I won’t be affected anymore by any sort of judgement from whoever reads this. So, here goes nothing:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is sunrise like at the pinnacle of human knowledge?</title><link href="https://jaydevsr.github.io/blog/thoughts/at-the-pinnacle-of-knowledge/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is sunrise like at the pinnacle of human knowledge?" /><published>2023-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jaydevsr.github.io/blog/thoughts/at-the-pinnacle-of-knowledge</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jaydevsr.github.io/blog/thoughts/at-the-pinnacle-of-knowledge/"><![CDATA[<iframe width="200" height="100" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/IP34E-ozwEM" title="Into The Universe With Stephen Hawking   The Story of Everything" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" class="side-note"></iframe>

<p>One of my earliest memories of anything to with physics is the introduction of Stephan Hawking’s show “Into the Universe”.
Through his computer voice while sitting in a majestic and empty hall which seems to be somewhere in Cambridge he says,
“Hello, My name is Stephan Hawking, physicist, cosmologist and something of a dreamer. Although I cannot move and I have to speak 
through a computer, in my mind I am free…”.<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> Now that is what I call a banger intro enough to excite any 12 year old <sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, 
isn’t it?<sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> Anyway the point is, this show was a major canon event in my life.</p>

<p>I usually only got to watch the Discovery channel when I got hand on the TV remote when my grandfater was out on the fields and 
my siblings were sleeping or playing with their friends. The TV was is in the corner of a small room which was in striking
contrast to the beautiful hall in which Hawking hosts the show from. This is what makes technology absolutely beautiful. Two
strikingly different worlds connected by a thread of EM waves, through a series of marvels of human engineering. All in 
all I don’t think I have watched this show more that two or three times but all of this was enough to make me wanting to 
introduce myself as a physicist as well.</p>

<p>Now to think that I am at the same place that used to be Hawking’s academic home is somewhat of an unblievable thing for 
me. To reach here consisted of multiple rounds of overcoming mediocrity to again be mediocre in the next one. 
So, now I am mediocre at one of the most brilliant places on this planet. I believe most of the people with whom I share this 
romantic journey in the pursuit of scientific knowledge have similar experiences. After all we all we not born geniuses and we all 
will not reach the final round where we are just mediocre among a handful of genius thinkers. But that’s okay because no 
one other than myself cares about if I ever do reach there.</p>

<p>The journey in itself is nothing like something a child would ever dream of. It doesn’t consist of a devoted study of natural world, 
through pure passion and lack of worries. The world is a harsh place full of suffering no matter what we do or where we are.
Life is not all fun just because we are pursuing our passion, it is just as difficult while making faliures a lot more frightening.
Realising this is one of the first signs of what they call growing up, in my opinion.</p>

<p>Today was a classic Sunday for me when I try to weigh the burden of my responsibilities and expectations from myself and 
feel bad about the distance from my ideal self. In midst of all this I let my mind wonder and fantasize about a life of just 
studying physics for the sake of it. In this meaningless detour from my usual line of thought I romatisised the 
vedic Rishis devoid of any other responsibility than the pursuit of knowledge and the mythical achievements of Taansen 
who through utter devotion to his music is said to have controlled the elements.</p>

<p>Although I am fully aware that these fantasies can never materialise in my lifetime.<sup id="fnref:4" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> Still in the end I realised what 
I think is the true nature of a physicist’s life. It is just a normal life with all of the usual bullshit but scattered 
with random events leading to discoveries and fame. In the end it just comes down to luck and preparation to make use of 
the gifts of randomness. We can’t control the former but the latter is in our hands and is the reason behind all the thing we 
have to go thorough which seem meaningless at first.</p>

<p>I think after this I can try to make peace with that all of the uninteresting coursework, difficult exams, useless research, 
unfinished projects and the brutal competetion for maintaining the right to keep doing all of these things. In the end, if 
all of this helps me catch a discovery in the wild I think it is worth it. Because in the end I love the thought of going to sleep 
while being the only one knowing the answer to one of nature’s infinitely many puzzles and to wake up 
to announce it to the whole world.<sup id="fnref:5" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote" rel="footnote">5</a></sup> I wonder, <strong>“what is sunrise like at the pinnacle of human knowledge?”</strong> <sup id="fnref:6" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote" rel="footnote">6</a></sup> I 
really want to know! If you know what it’s like please tell me and if not then I will surely let you know if I ever see 
it for myself.</p>

<h2 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h2>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>I did see this show in Hindi which was thankfully translated without sabotaging the original english sentence. But one weird thing was the translation was so pure, completely devoid of Urdu that it was a bit dense for me at that time. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>I am not completely sure of my age at that time, could be more or less but the deviation is small I think. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>I think this won’t do it for the 12 yo’s today, for which I am very thankful that we didn’t have fortnite, minecraft and the weird horror games that I have seen kids play. Yes I do sound like an uncle but I honestly don’t mind at this point, which can be taken as another reason to call me an uncle <sup id="fnref:7" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:7" class="footnote" rel="footnote">7</a></sup>. Go on I dare you. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Honestly, I don’t even think I want such a life for myself. I am the kind of person who can’t give up eating delicious food and sleeping half dead with my ass saluting the heavens. <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:5" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>As an example I have always ended up thinking about the discovery of the structure of DNA and Circk announcing it to the world in the Eagle pub whenever I have passed by it. <a href="#fnref:5" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:6" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>I use “human knowledge” and not just knowledge because who knows maybe aliens… Haha. Anyway I used to watch this show Ancient Aliens a lot with my brother, the show was utter bullshit which I was aware of but for some reason it was very entertaining at that time. Now I just can’t even watch its clips without cringing to my bones. <a href="#fnref:6" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:7" role="doc-endnote">
      <p><em>For someone reading while unaware of the Indian salutation system</em>: I mean uncle as in the term used to refer to someone in your previous generation who may not actually be your uncle. <a href="#fnref:7" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Jaydev</name></author><category term="Thoughts" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">It is raining and it’s not for me.</title><link href="https://jaydevsr.github.io/blog/thoughts/it-is-raining-and-it-is-not-for-me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="It is raining and it’s not for me." /><published>2022-06-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-06-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jaydevsr.github.io/blog/thoughts/it-is-raining-and-it-is-not-for-me</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jaydevsr.github.io/blog/thoughts/it-is-raining-and-it-is-not-for-me/"><![CDATA[<p>Clouds had been slowly taking over the sky since afternoon. I knew it was going to rain but the faint lightning in the sky attracted me. I couldn’t just sit in my dark room, by the way which was dark to keep the bugs out. Usually, I don’t like to stay outside with lightning over my head but this time it was at some great distance so I went for a walk.</p>

<p>I love solo walks. This is not an overstatement. And I specially like them with some music. I put on Beethoven’s ‘Kreutzer’, which I wanted to listen to again after hearing it in an anime. It was hitting the mood just right and got me lost in my own world. And then it happened. The rain.</p>

<p>I was not running at first but I had no power over the mighty clouds I would say. They showed me my place. I started running quickly, the sonata was reaching its end as well and just when the last note struck I made it to where I was running to, the hostel entrance.</p>

<p>Usually I am egocentric and would tend to build the world around me but not this time. Maybe because of sunday evening mood and the music, I don’t know. But I realised one thing for sure, <strong>it was raining and it was not for me</strong>.</p>

<p>It was neither raining for me nor for the people around me. It would have rained even if we were not there. Such realisation is not good for the human nature. We want to feel important, wanted and probably also immortal by the virtue of the deeds. But no cloud has ever paid attention to such desires because they are part of something truely immortal. But this thought calmed me.</p>

<p>Rains have always had a calming effect on me. I never dug in deep to find the reason but this evening it came to me. I feel calm when I am not the origin of my world. I always used to sit in my window while it was raining back home and feel the tiny droplets on my face. The droplets felt cold but my heart always felt warm and it dissolved the cage around me for me to build again. This was probably the start of my romance with the monsoon. So, I balantly claim monsoon to be my favorite season despite hating mud and, loving mangoes in summer and sleeping under a heavy blanket in winter more than anything. I still haven’t found many people making such claims but it is what it is.</p>]]></content><author><name>Jaydev</name></author><category term="Thoughts" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Clouds had been slowly taking over the sky since afternoon. I knew it was going to rain but the faint lightning in the sky attracted me. I couldn’t just sit in my dark room, by the way which was dark to keep the bugs out. Usually, I don’t like to stay outside with lightning over my head but this time it was at some great distance so I went for a walk.]]></summary></entry></feed>